so let's say that we have these five
instructions and for now all that
matters really for right after I
dependencies which registers are we
writing to so let's say that the first
instruction is writing to r1 it's
computing some result it doesn't really
matter what it is and then the second
one is writing to r4 then we have our
seven and our eight being written and
then the fifth instruction is also
supposed to write to our four so we will
see that the problem will be with the
second and the fifth instruction writing
to r4 so what can happen is let's say
that there is a read after write
dependence between the first and the
second instructions so what's now going
to happen is there will be some cycle
let's call it cycle five in which r1 is
going to execute our four cannot execute
it has to wait and it will execute here
in cycle six meanwhile these
instructions will execute because they
don't have any dependencies now in our
five stage pipeline what's going to
happen is basically this instruction is
then going to move to the mem stage
where it doesn't do anything because
none of them are really memory
instructions and then so will these and
then what's going to happen is in the
next cycle this instruction will write
its result
so now r1 gets written this instruction
is also gonna write its results so r7 is
going to be written this one writes r8
and this one writes are four however the
second instruction has executed here so
it's going to go through the mem stage
here and write the result here and it's
going to be r4 so if you look at what's
the final result in our for the final
result is in r4 is whatever was the last
thing written to it which is going to be
this value but it should have been this
value because when the programmer wrote
this they wrote it this way so they
would expect that our four would retain
the value from this fifth instruction
not from the instruction so basically
the programmer wanted this to become
temporarily this but then take a new
value here and that's kind of the last
value after these five instructions but
that didn't happen so that's a problem
why is it a problem why did it occur
because this instruction got delayed so
we have executed these two instructions
out of order this is the second
instruction and it writes in the eighth
cycle this is the fifth instruction but
it writes in the seventh cycle so
basically we have actually written the
result in the wrong order
I mean it's it's an order different from
the order in which they were supposed to
execute in the program so in order to
fix this one solution would be so to fix
this one solution would be to not have
this instruction right the result here
instead it would have to be stalled here
and here and finally write its result
here so a real processor might in some
way needs to figure out how to do this
because these writes need to happen in
the correct order